<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Bhargav's Homepage - meta</title><link href="https://bhargavbhat.me/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://bhargavbhat.me/feeds/meta.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://bhargavbhat.me/</id><updated>2021-11-01T14:31:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>Moving to Pelican &amp; Reclaiming Old Writing</title><link href="https://bhargavbhat.me/moving-to-pelican-reclaiming-old-writing.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-11-01T14:31:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-11-01T14:31:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Bhargav Bhat</name></author><id>tag:bhargavbhat.me,2021-11-01:/moving-to-pelican-reclaiming-old-writing.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Moving to Pelican and Reclaiming Old writing across notes, text files, emails and shared docs&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This post is just a summary of me doing a Deepawali cleaning of all of my notes, old emails, text files and Google Drive stuff and moving it all under a managable blog hosted on GitHub pages with &lt;a href="https://docs.getpelican.com/en/latest/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Installation &amp;amp; Theme Selection&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pelican install was very quick and straight forward process, just follow the instructions laid out in the "quickstart" section of the docs and a fully functional, ready to serve blog was ready on my local machine. This also allowed me to try out a few themes, verify formatting (most of the posts I have were written a email, text files or shared docs, not markdown) and ensure that everything looked fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Theme selection was a slighly longer task, mostly consisted of &lt;a href="http://www.pelicanthemes.com/"&gt;browsing&lt;/a&gt; available options, trawling the respective github repos and picking one that clicked visually and feature-wise. Then came the testing phase of trying it on the articles and pages that I had migrated/created so far. My main criteria for theme selection were a clean design, pleasing colours, tags &amp;amp; categories support along with a search function. Although I couldn't find one that checked all the boxes, I found that &lt;a href="https://github.com/laughk/pelican-hss"&gt;pelican-hss&lt;/a&gt; had all that I wanted (save the search function). I picked that theme, made a few tweaks to the supplied pygments CSS and &lt;code&gt;base.html&lt;/code&gt; template and decided to call it a day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Deployment to Github Pages&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My previous homepage was a rather simple landing page, with links to social media profiles:
&lt;img alt="Previous Homepage" src="https://bhargavbhat.me/images/home_page.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and this was served out of github pages as a simple &lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt; file, forked from the html5up repo. Moving to pelican meant setting up branches slightly differently. I chose to use the &lt;code&gt;content&lt;/code&gt; branch to contain all of the Pelican stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Learning&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real power, flexibility &amp;amp; convenience of static hosting is apparent from all of the personal blogs and project pages hosted on GH pages. For me, a lot of the learning was around pelican,setting up venv right and migrating content&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Road Ahead&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of my old notes, shared docs and learning are still scattered all over platforms. Although not too many public/shared posts and notes exist, I still have to sift through them all, deal with dead links and filter out stuff that's relevant and applicable to a wider audience. Most of the notes that I have are specific to the particular teams, products or siutations. I've gotten thru a few of these notes and will continue to add them to the site as fast as I can. As I make my way around this old stuff, a lot more posts should start popping up on the homepage. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: Dates and stuff for these old posts is from file meta data, may not be 100% accurate. Stuff that was once WIP has likely been abandoned and/or is no longer relevant. Links have been updated and dead links removed (where applicable). If you find something odd or inaccurate, please do reach out. :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="meta"></category></entry><entry><title>Working at a Startup : Notes &amp; Observations</title><link href="https://bhargavbhat.me/working-at-a-startup-notes-observations.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-30T19:53:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-12-30T19:53:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Bhargav Bhat</name></author><id>tag:bhargavbhat.me,2016-12-30:/working-at-a-startup-notes-observations.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Notes and observations after working for 6 months at a startup&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In Jul 2016, I switched to a new role as a Tech Lead at an Internet of Things (IoT) focused startup. Prior to this, my career was with MNCs of various sizes. This is a reflection of the change 6months into the new company&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This past July, I finally made the plunge and joined a startup. The opportunity was too good to pass up - focus on IoT and work on an in-house product as well as helping customers realize thier vision for connected devices and next-gen connectivity technologies. Technically, this was the perfect mix for the stage of career I was at. Now, 6 months on, I am glad to have taken this step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Culture Shock&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone that was associated with MNCs all throughout their professional career, this switch was somewhat of a culture shock, but in a good way :). The fast-paced, efficiency focused style of working, having only as much process in place as necessary and the constant multi-tasking between unrelated asks was very new. Loosely structured days and a higher level of autonomy were welcome changes as well. Also new was the more-or-less constantly connected nature of the role and the blurring boundaries between "office" and "home". Flex-hours and Work-from-Home (sometimes for an entire week leading upto holidays) was an interesting experience for me. However, all said and done, I really found this new position expanding my horizons on what different styles of working looked like. After a couple of days being confused and bewildered, I was able to get into the groove and it all started feeling natural a couple of weeks in. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Learning&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I'm pretty sure there's a lot more to learn, 6 months in, here's the most impactful learnings since joining this position:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plan ahead and communicate prefer communication over written medium : Flex-time and WFH make this more or less essential for communication outside of scheduled meetings and Agile ceremonies&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Constant Adaptation : Even with a good plan in place, things outside one's control will force change in course. The only way forward is to adapt constantly&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Failure is an Option : In certain contexts, it is definitely preferable to fail fast and course correct rather than spend precious few resources on big obstacles&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multi-tasking : While most professionals will multi-task on a daily basis, the range or breadth of tasks would be rather limited. This is not really the case in a startup with limited engineering staff and multiple unrealted programs running in parallel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning on the Job : is more or less a requirement and combined with constant adaptation and accepting &amp;amp; moving on from failures, one's learning is accelerated manyfold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Road Ahead&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This journey has just started for me professionally and I'm sure there is a lot more this onion than the few layers I've managed to peel as yet. From guiding &amp;amp; mentoring to leading and working through people, there is a lot more for me to discover.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="meta"></category></entry></feed>