<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Bhargav's Homepage - tools</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/tools.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2014-11-01T20:33:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>Overleaf - Online LaTeX Editor</title><link href="/overleaf-online-latex-editor.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-11-01T20:33:00+05:30</published><updated>2014-11-01T20:33:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Bhargav Bhat</name></author><id>tag:None,2014-11-01:/overleaf-online-latex-editor.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;TIL about Overleaf the online LaTeX Editor&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been using &lt;a href="https://www.latex-project.org/about/"&gt;LaTeX&lt;/a&gt; to typeset my resume for a while. The advantages are many:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plain-text format, can be added into version control&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relatively easy to export to multiple formats : PDF, Word (via &lt;code&gt;pandoc&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Precise positioning of elements and easier to possible to tweak formatting of certain sections or parts without ruining the formatting of the entire document&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reuse and Automation (environments and commands etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My resume is based on a modified version of this &lt;a href="https://github.com/treyhunner/resume"&gt;template&lt;/a&gt; and is a simple 2-pager without too many custom elements. However, to compile and generate it on the fly meant I would need an installation of LaTeX on my laptop or a VM that I could SSH into. This was a minor incovenience, that could be worked around by having a compiled PDF in the same repo as the resume itself and that's precisely what I did until I learnt about &lt;a href="https://www.overleaf.com"&gt;Overleaf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overleaf is an awesome website that lets you import existing LaTeX projects and provides the facility to compile them into a PDF that you can download. It also has rudimentary form of workspace separation and limted version control/history features. Where I found it lacking was on the collaboration front, as far as I can see there is no straightforward way to "invite" people to edit or review your files (a-la Google Docs) and nor is there a way to send or share the final output PDF with users via email (short of downloading the PDF yourself and sharing that directly). I sure do hope they add these features soon :) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: Obligatory LaTeX resume &lt;a href="http://stevehanov.ca/blog/?id=56"&gt;joke&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="tools"></category><category term="latex"></category><category term="til"></category></entry></feed>