<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Bhargav's Homepage - tool</title><link href="https://bhargavbhat.me/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://bhargavbhat.me/feeds/tool.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://bhargavbhat.me/</id><updated>2019-10-07T21:34:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>TIL Darktable</title><link href="https://bhargavbhat.me/til-darktable.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-10-07T21:34:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-10-07T21:34:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Bhargav Bhat</name></author><id>tag:bhargavbhat.me,2019-10-07:/til-darktable.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A chance encounter with Darktable and dabbling with this interesting tool&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Since I got hold of a DSLR a little over 3years ago and years of using loaners before that, I've been using &lt;a href="https://www.rawtherapee.com/"&gt;rawtherapee&lt;/a&gt; to process the raw files from cameras. I started with v4.2 of the program and I'm currently using v5.6 that was released just a few months ago. It works well with Shotwell and produces pretty good results. &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ccUv02QFMxs"&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; tutorial covers the worflow for rawtherapee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mostly use rawtherapee for basic edits : slight exposure tweaks, crops and the occasional horizon straightening. Along with the usual suspects: noise reduction, profiled lens correction, whitebalance, contrast &amp;amp; saturation. Today, I was looking at getting a few more of my old raw files processed and before I started the process, I first wanted to see a summary video or two of the new stuff in v5.6. However, the YouTube suggestion algorithm had a different fate planned and surfaced &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Fv8yKb0oLJM"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; interesting video, and that was how I was introduced to darktable :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After spending most of the day looking into more darktable videos (instead of actually working on the raw files), here is what I was able to take away:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;darktable and rawtherapee use a bunch of the same libraries to get a lot of the "plumbing" done. Each has a different approach though.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;darktable supports one feature (still) missing in rawtherapee : masks for selective application of edits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;darktable supports one other feature (still) missing in rawtherapee : spot-removal (handy to get rid of dustbins and such)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;darktable has a batch-processing capability (copy/paste/save history) for quickly dealing with a bunch of similar images, similar to Paste Partial, but more granular&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;darktable has a cleaner UI (reminiscent of Lightroom) and a "favourites" options to pin/arrange tools as per your liking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... so does that mean I'm moving over to darktable? Well, just like with the whole vim vs nvim thing a couple of years ago, I'll probably have both installed for a while and then make a choice based on what "feels" right after a few months of use :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="tool"></category><category term="photography"></category><category term="darktable"></category><category term="rawtherapee"></category></entry><entry><title>mbed Simulator</title><link href="https://bhargavbhat.me/mbed-simulator.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-10-01T12:26:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-10-01T12:26:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Bhargav Bhat</name></author><id>tag:bhargavbhat.me,2018-10-01:/mbed-simulator.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;TIL mbed simulator online tool&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today, I came across the online simulator for mbed, available &lt;a href="https://simulator.mbed.com/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Although it is currently marked as "experimental", this simulator is pretty full featured and allows developers to test their mbed OS 5 applications without really having to go thru the while code-build-flash-test cycle. Although it doesn't claim to be cycle-accurate, it is really a handy way to test code written against mbed and also for learning/lab environments where this tool can definitely reduce the need for physical devkits or boards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tool was announced earlier this year during the mbed conference and details about the tool are available &lt;a href="https://os.mbed.com/blog/entry/introducing-mbed-simulator/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The associated &lt;a href="https://github.com/ARMmbed/mbed-connect-2018-simulator"&gt;code repo&lt;/a&gt; has a bunch of interesting samples including ones that demonstrate the networking capabilities of the simulator.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="tool"></category><category term="simulator"></category><category term="mbed"></category></entry></feed>